this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
softball are you looking for a better
way to track your engineering backlog do
you want a project management tool
that's both powerful and a joy to use
give clubhouse a try designed for
software teams clubhouse is a fast
modern alternative to conventional
project management tools that are either
too complex are too simple start your
free trial and get two extra free months
at clubhouse io / se radio for software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today I have with me Joshua Davies
Joshua is a software developer with over
20 years of experience in diverse
languages including Java C Python Ruby
and JavaScript he holds a master's
degree in computer science from the
University of Texas at Arlington he's
currently a senior software architect at
sirius XM radio and has previously
worked as a consultant with major brand
name client Joshua is the author of the
book implementing SSL and TLS using
cryptography and PKI
today judgment I will be talking about
topics around the implementation of TLS
in PKI Joshua welcome to software
engineering radio thank you for having
me you like to add anything to your
biography that I didn't mention okay
this show it will not exactly be a
introductory show about TLS and PKI but
some of the details we leave out are
covering a lot of detail in your book so
I will refer those sinners to the book
if they want more information we're
going to focus on some of the edge cases
vulnerabilities and implementation
issues both
or web clients and people implementing
web applications but having said that I
would like to start out with a brief
introduction - we'll start with TLS and
then we'll move on to PK I tell us what
is TLS all right
so in 1995 the Netscape corporation
started developing the first commercial
web browser and they recognized
correctly that nobody was going to trust
this new thing unless it could provide
some kind of security so they hired dr.
Tyrell Kemal to design the SSL protocol
for them and the SSL stands for Secure
Sockets Layer and it's a really good
implementation of cryptography and the
public key infrastructure that we're
going to talk a little bit more about
that provides a lot of security under
the assumptions that the network is
completely hostile that people are
trying to spy on you that people are
intercepting your packets and trying to
make modifications and even in the face
of that kind of a hostile network SSL is
designed to stand up and provide privacy
and security and integrity to all of
your communications it does a really
good job of it in it was 1995 or 96 when
SSL version 3 was released by Netscape
and it was part of Netscape commerce
server and Netscape Navigator of the
browser that kind of morphed into what
we now call Firefox and although they
were very open about the protocol they
wanted everybody else to use it there
was some concern at the time about a
private company like Netscape managing
this protocol that was basically
underpinning the entire worldwide web so
they turned that over to the internet
Engineering Task Force one of the first
things that the internet Engineering
Task Force at the IETF is the same guys
who specify TCP and IP and BGP and ARP
and everything that makes the internet
run the first one of the first things
they did was they renamed it from SSL
which stands for Secure Sockets Layer
dat TLS which stands for transport layer
security
there wasn't any good
even given for doing that and it's kind
of unfortunate that they did because the
term SSL is still used far more often
than TLS however SSL has been proper SSL
which is SSL v3 is specified by Netscape
in 1996 has been completely deprecated
you're not using it nobody's using it if
you're using it you're in trouble you're
using TLS but we still call it SSL the
primary the most popular library for TLS
is called open SSL the most popular
auditing software for TLS is called
Qualis SSL labs and I don't think the
term SSL is ever going to go away even
though nobody uses SSL I want to
highlight a couple of things you said by
security can mean many different things
by privacy you mean encryption and
integrity I mean some sort of hashing or
guarantee that the content has not been
altered in transit is that correct
that's right
privacy protects you against passive
eavesdroppers anybody who is going
trying to just look at what you're
communicating integrity protects you
against active attackers who might
actually try to modify something that
you're sending it's harder to modify
something that's encrypted but it's not
impossible if an attacker knows certain
positions in a ciphertext and other
positions he knows where variable data
can be inserted
he can take bits and pieces from non
integrity a non hashed bit of packet and
can insert that somewhere so SSL in TLS
technically in addition to providing
privacy through encryption also provides
integrity through hashing functions
anytime during this interview you say
SSL where you mean TLS I'll give you a
pass on that so don't worry about it
because everybody else calls it as a
cell that's right okay now I want to get
a little bit into the type of encryption
and the use of is asymmetric keys can
you explain how how the encryption gets
set up
in the TLS handshake right so we talked
about there's two types of encryption
that are used by SSL there's symmetric
encryption and asymmetric or public key
encryption so symmetric encryption is
kind of what most of us think of when we
think of secret code so they've been
around since there were militaries and
spy craft that us a symmetric encryption
method is one where you and I want to
exchange a private message so we share a
secret but that secret is called a key
and I use that secret to encode my
message you see use that secret to
decode it only you can read it because
only you have the key and that works
well if there's a way for us to
communicate beforehand and exchange this
secret in such a way that nobody else
can see it let me let me just get an
example of me so I'm gonna send you a
number but we meet and agree beforehand
that I'm going to add +1 to the number
and you get it and you just subtract one
but somebody sees me sending you a six
they don't know is that the true number
did I multiply it by two or did I add
seven because they don't know the key
that's right and that's a variant of
what's called the Caesar cipher that was
actually used in military cryptography
thousands of years ago okay so proceed
yeah so and the state of cryptography
was that you had to meet before hand in
exchange secret keys until about 1977
when a couple of cryptographers named
Whitfield Diffie and Martin Hellman came
up with the diffie-hellman key exchange
and it's actually pretty straightforward
but it's a really interesting way of
taking advantage of the distributivity
of the modulus operator to exchange a
key securely in such a way that you can
do it right in front of everybody and
they still can't see what was actually
exchanged and it's actually simple
enough that I can go through it here
without a whiteboard and visual aids the
idea is that we just you and I in front
of everybody we pick two numbers G and P
right we agree on those numbers and
anybody can hear us say those numbers
now I pick a number act
and I compute G to the X mod P and I
tell you the result I don't tell you X
you pick another number Y and you
compute G to the Y mod P you tell me the
result you don't tell me why then I turn
around I take your result raise it to my
power X mod P and you take your result
the result that I send you raise it to
your secret number Y to the mod P and
because because the exponentiation
operator and the modulus operator are
both distributive we're going to end up
with the same number and we could turn
around and use that secret number that
nobody else can see and nobody else can
compute backwards to find as our secret
key it's a brilliant but very simple bit
of math that's really saved a lot of a
lot of complexity in computers
communication for this to work it relies
on
I could say the commutativity of this
mathematical operator that we can both
do the same operation in different order
and call that same thing commutativity
and distributivity that's right okay so
how does this process fit into the TLS
handshake in order to enable us to
communicate with encryption right so i'm
gonna open up my browser and i'm gonna
go to amazon.com and i want to encrypt
everything so the first thing my
browser's gonna do is it's gonna send
what's called a client hello message to
Amazon and it's gonna say hey I know how
to do diffie-hellman key exchange or
there are other key exchanges like RSA
key exchange and elliptic curve
diffie-hellman key exchange and I also
know how to do symmetric cryptography
methods like Triple DES or idea or
Blowfish or to fish or AES and as well
as certain Mac are hashing operations so
the server is gonna look at what I say I
can support it's gonna pick one and it's
gonna turn around and it's going to
initiate a key exchange with me we're
going to exchange a key we're going to
agree on a secret key that's used for
the symmetric cryptography and we're
going to start encrypting everything as
well as hashing and
H macking everything from that point
forward and at that point it becomes
completely transparent as far as the
browser and the server are concerned
we're still just doing regular HTTP it
can't even tell if there's SSL going on
under the scenes okay so I'd like to
then move into PKI and then the goal
here is we're gonna get to HTTPS which
is a way that TLS and PKI work together
with HTTP so let's let's move on to PKI
I mean you'd start with what does that
stand for and then to tell us what that
is yeah so pki stands for public key
infrastructure so one of the
vulnerabilities of the diffie-hellman
key exchange and and any other key
exchange is what's called the
man-in-the-middle attack if I'm only
looking if I'm only concerned about
passive eavesdroppers diffie-hellman is
perfect I can use diffie-hellman to do a
key exchange and then I can use that to
encrypt data but if somebody can get in
the middle it's called a
man-in-the-middle or but I've also heard
it called a monster in the middle I
don't know if that's politically correct
or if that's just a way of telling you
how bad it is but if somebody can get in
the middle and start changing things it
can actually modify these packets before
I send them what he can do is he can
complete a diffie-hellman handshake
between he and I and the diffie-hellman
handshake at the same time between he
and you and intercept the secret key so
you think you did a key exchange with me
I think I did a key exchange for you but
we both actually did a key exchange with
him and he knows the secret keys and
he's just decrypting everything reading
it Rhian crypting it and sending it back
on to you so the way you can guard
against that is a digital signature at
the end of the whole handshake process I
want to say okay what I sent you was
blah blah blah blah blah and it's signed
this way to prove that I really sent it
so digital signature algorithm is kind
of like an inverted key agreement DSA
which stands for digital signature
algorithm the government came up with
that one
is a standard signature algorithm RSA is
also used to do digital signatures and
the idea is kind of similar to a diffi
Hellman key exchange in that there are
two numbers called the public key and
private key that are related
mathematically such that I can perform
an operation with the private key and a
message that you given the public key
can verify that only I came up with
because only I have access to the
private key so okay great it works well
so I tell you what my public key was
then we do a key exchange and then I
used my private key to sign the whole
key exchange and say ok check the public
key and make sure that this was really
me the only problem is now how do you
know that public he really came from me
and not the man in the middle right
we've just moved the goal posts right
and I see this it's a theme of looking
into this entire field is you have this
thing that somehow we need to know or
establish and you can't definitely
establish that because many mental
problems so then you kick it one layer
down and say well there's this other
system which will tell us that and that
just moves the vulnerability one layer
up or downstream it does and the
solution is actually like you said
Turtles all the way down it's when I
send you my public key my public key has
also been signed by yet another public
key that you already trust and that
public key is called a certificate
authority and that certificate authority
is built into your browser and that has
to be set up ahead of time but that's
better than you everybody who wants to
communicate setting up a pre-established
trust relationship ahead of time then
you know I can trust just a handful of
certificate authorities that I hopefully
I have a lot of confidence in to really
essentially vouch for people when they
say hey I'm Josh Davies and my private
key is 1 2 3 4 5 the certificate
authority says yes his provo key is
really 1 2 3 4 5 you
and trust that anybody who can prove
ownership of the private key associated
with that public he is really Josh
Davies we will be talking quite a lot
about certificate authorities but before
we get to that I think it would be good
to talk about what what is a certificate
in particular the x.509 standard yeah so
I've been talking about public keys and
identities kind of as an amorphous blob
but when a public key is exchanged its
exchanged wrapped up in an x.509
certificate the PKI public key
infrastructure when you talk about PKI
you're really talking about x.509
certificates and the keys that they wrap
and those have been around since 1989
since long before before even browsers
really this decideed had been floating
around for quite a while so x.509 is
just a standard for representing subject
for example josh davies or brook robert
bloomin and the private key that's
associated with them along with the
signature of the certificate authority
that vouches for the validity of this
certificate along with some other things
like a serial number so that you can
tell one certificate from another and a
validity period so I can say this is my
public key until 2021 but don't trust it
after that so the particular what you've
established is you could provide a
certificate and that certificate was
signed by someone that I trust and I in
the location bar of my browser it says
amazon.com how exactly do I know that
that certificate that we're using in
this conversation is the amazon.com
certificate right so the public key
infrastructure the x509 x500 directory
that was developed in the late 80s was
really designed for people to identify
human beings subjects so you'll see
things like country and location and
organization and organization unit as
well as
subject name so if you want to repurpose
that general concept to something like a
browser you know what what is amazon.com
it's you know it's www.amazon.com I've
added with that public key and check to
see if that Association of that public
key to that domain name was actually
signed by a trusted certificate
authority there's there's a then there
is a field somewhere in the x.509
certificate in this case it would say
WWE amazon.com is the value of that
field and that better match the location
that I'm think I'd better match the DNS
name that I think I'm communicating with
that's right it has to match exactly
what you typed into your browser bar it
it used to be that that was put into the
common name field of the x.509
certificate it's become more common to
use an extension field called DC which
stands for domain name component where
they actually pass in they give you DC
equals W WWDC equals Amazon DC equals
comm I don't know if there's any
particular benefit in doing it that way
but certificates have shifted from using
the common name which is supposed to
identify person to an actual domain
component which identifies an actual
domain but yes if you connect to WWE
amazon.com and you get a certificate
with a common name or a DC of wwo com
your browser will close the connection
immediately at this point we have all
the pieces and we can proceed to the
question what is the difference between
HTTP and HTTPS yeah well really the
difference is just the existence of SSL
plain old HTTP you establish it the
browser establishes TCP connection once
the TCP connection
does its three-way handshake and the
first thing it's gonna do is it's gonna
send say GE T get space slash index dot
HTML space HTTP slash 1.1 followed by
some headers and crlf to terminate the
request and it's gonna expect a response
so HTTP does the TCP handshake then it
does an SSL handshake and then using the
encrypted layer sends GE T space slash
index dot HTML space HTTP slash 1.1 now
so the server that accepts the
connection has to have some way of
knowing that you're going to turn around
do an SSL handshake versus sending
unencrypted HTTP and the way most
browsers do that or really the way
everybody does that is they listen on
two different ports port 84 unencrypted
HTTP in port 443 for SSL so if I connect
to port 443 the server expects the next
byte to be an SSL client hello byte
there's another optional piece of this
which I find kind of interesting called
server name indication you talk about
that yeah so it was very popular in the
90s when it cost a lot to host a website
I suppose it's still a lot of people
doing it to do virtual hosting right
where you had one IP address that
correspond to multiple hosts so I could
connect two IP address 1.2.3.4 for
example and say okay get me
Roberts shoes.com and the virtual hosts
were spot responsible for checking to
see ok I got to go to this directory for
Roberts shoes.com and this directory for
Josh's hats comm so that it presents a
problem for HTTP because we haven't sent
it just knows the IP address I'm
connecting to it doesn't know what
hostname I'm looking for
and it can't find out what hostname I'm
looking for until it's established a
connection but it can't establish a
connection without giving me the
certificate associated with that host so
one of the extensions to the SSL client
hello is the server name indicator that
says okay the host I really want is
Roberts shoes.com
that tells the server which is which
certificate to actually present I'm
aware that there were some major
upgrades in the TLS 1.3 version what did
what did he do there yeah so TLS tls/ssl
is on its sixth revision now there was
SSL v2 that was deprecated pretty
quickly by Netscape SSL v3 then the IETF
took over and created TLS 100 which at
the wire protocol level is actually
called SSL 3.1 then we had TLS 1.1 in
2006 TLS 1.2 in 2008 and we just got TLS
1.3 I want to say a year ago it was
finalized now SSL v3 TLS 100 TLS 1.1 and
TLS 1.2 are very similar as a matter of
fact you can implement the code for SSL
v3 TLS 1.2 LS 1.1 with a difference of
about 20 or 30 lines of code and if you
want to see how you can read my book I
should show exactly how to do that TLS
1.2 introduces a few more concepts so
it's a little different but it's still
very similar to its predecessors TLS 1.3
is very very different they focused on
efficiency and they focused on privacy
in the TLS 1.3 release one of the big
changes that they made is that it used
to take as many as seven different back
and forth messages to establish an SSL
connection they've compressed that down
to about three in TLS 1.3 in most cases
the big change they did to do that is
they let the client start the key
exchange and the client can just
assumes that the server will be able to
support its preferred method of key
exchange if it's wrong the server can
say hope you got to start back over I
don't know how to talk that way and they
just do a regular almost a TLS 1.2 style
handshake at that point but in almost
every case the server does actually
support the clients preferred method of
key exchange so they can save a whole
round trip that way and speed things up
they also introduced the concept of what
they call zero RTT handshake where the
client can assume that the server can do
a handshake assume that the server can
do encryption and if there's already key
established from a previous session go
ahead and send some encrypted data in
the very first message along with the
client along with the client hello now
there's some risk there because if
that's vulnerable to replay attacks
where somebody grabs that client hello
and sends it again again with that
what's called the early data the zero
RTT data and the server has no way of
recognizing that but for simple things
like you know just to get the home page
type of request get index.html that's
actually a big win in terms of speed
what extent is reducing the number of
round trips driven by the increasing use
of mobile phones where every trip over
the mobile network is quite costly and
there's a greater concern about battery
life yeah that was a driver as well as
you know most sites you get big sites
like Sirius XM where I work or Amazon or
Google or Travelocity where I used to
work they have these huge server farms
they don't just have one computer
serving web request they have you know
hundreds and hundreds of machines
serving requests so what they have to do
in order for all of those servers to
look to the outside world like a single
server they have to have a load balancer
and in order to have a load balancer
that speaks SSL they have to terminate
SSL essentially do the
Crypton at the load balancer and then
send that request on to the box that's
actually responsible for doing the
response so when you have a load
balancer that's getting millions and
millions and millions of requests and
you know in milliseconds it really start
to add up wanna move on now we've
covered the foundations and we're going
to be talking more about above all their
abilities they most are all of the
vulnerabilities that I encountered
researching this have to do with the man
in the middle which you define could we
go more into what is some of the damage
that could be caused by
man-in-the-middle attacks if you're
aware of any instances that have been
known to the public because I understand
a lot of attacks are never disclosed
yeah I don't know that anybody's ever
executed a man-in-the-middle in
exfiltrated data and been shown to have
exfiltrated data that way usually we're
just told that you know Equifax was
hacked
for example we and we don't know if that
was cross-site request forgery we don't
know if that was cross-site scripting
sequel injection or if it was actually a
man-in-the-middle attack they don't
usually go into that level of detail but
if if somebody can insert themselves in
between you and the servers that you're
talking to they can not only read and
see everything that's it passed back and
forth you know including your credit
card numbers they can also modify data
they can change the data to say anything
they wanted to say which could be
catastrophic one then one type of value
gained by the attacker might be they
could observe credit card numbers or
maybe they could observe credentials
going by and use that for a subsequent
attack where they then break in and
start to do other types of damage or
exfiltration that's right I think man in
the middle themselves between the site
administrator and the website they can
get the site administrators password and
then take over the entire site
legitimate I want to move on now we are
going to spend some time talking about
certificate
authorities you earlier said the
certificate authorities an entity which
I trust to be the final signature of
this chain of certificates and that the
reason I trust them is that they're
built into the operating system or the
browser Oh what is a CA exactly
technically speaking a certificate
authority from the perspective of your
browser is just a certificate it's a
self signed certificate
so remember certificate is an
association between a subject or a
common name and a public key so that
certificate has to be signed by a
trusted Authority so okay well now now
we've got this recursive loop where
everything has to be signed at the top
level you can actually sign a
certificate using the public key that's
in the certificate of course that's
silly
unless you have some reason to already
trust it so as far as your browser is
concerned a certificate authority is
just a self-signed top-level certificate
that's already built into its trust
store whether that trust store is part
of the browser or whether that trust
store is part of the operating system
now from yours and my perspective as web
browsers or potentially web server
administrators the certificate authority
is an organization that's probably gonna
charge me money to sign my certificate
request associating my domain name with
the public key that I tell them is my
public key who are some of the
well-known certificate authorities in
the u.s. Verisign is a big one thought
is a big one I have trouble keeping up
with who who's buying who I think
Verisign was bought by Symantec a while
back GoDaddy is a big certificate
authority in its own right and it's it
also has hosting and let's encrypt is a
big certificate authority that actually
issues free certificates and we're
talking how much money are we talking to
buy a certificate for a domain it's
usually a few hundred dollars there's a
concept of what's called extended
validation where the certificate
authority can do a real vetting to
really really really check that you are
who you say you are and it costs a
little bit more but as it turns out the
only benefit to paying for an extended
validation is that your browser bar
turns green most users don't care if the
browser bar turns green so most people
don't care about getting extended
validation certificates we're gonna talk
a bit more about validation later I want
to stay on the ca's for now so the trust
store is it's on a computer it's then
it's a folder or maybe it could be a
database containing root certificates
right and if I looked on my Mac or
Windows machine how many root
certificates would I find well I have my
Mac open right now I have a hundred and
seventy seven root certificates all of
which can sign any website in the world
great how does the certificate authority
protect its own private keys well that's
gonna vary from one certificate
authority to the next some of them have
not always done a good job of doing that
Komodo had a leak where their private
keys were compromised and some
certificates were issued invalidly
they it's it's all operational it's all
policy because a lot of people have to
be able to use this private key because
the private key is really that's the
security right if the private key is
leaked the certificate authority is
compromised if the private key is safe
then the certificate authority can be
trusted and but a lot of people have to
be able to access that private key
because that they're in the business of
generating signatures using it so it
it's gonna be a lot of internal policies
and procedures to make sure that only
people who are trusted have access to
the machine or machines that have access
to that key and unfortunately that's
fairly fairly opaque process
certificate authorities are not very
open about how they do that now what are
the steps I start Robert's certificate
authority I'm gonna print money here are
gonna charge people five hundred dollars
to just sign their sign their
certificate signing request and how do I
get the browsers or operating system
vendors to include my root certificate
in their releases well Microsoft and
Apple both have online forms that you
can go fill out and just cut and paste a
public key and consider ask to be
considered as a top level certificate
authority in the operating system now
what sort of validations they do on you
that's that's internal that's opaque and
they're not very open about that for for
good reason so we don't really know what
these different certificate authorities
did to get included in the root
certificate store for the operating
system but some of them have not been
good players so we know that the vetting
process is not foolproof another podcast
I listened to called security now
there's a point they they constantly
hammering on this point that these
certificate authorities if you look at
them on a Windows machine there are the
well-known vendors from the United
States like GoDaddy another ones you
mentioned
and you'll see them from many different
countries at the point being I live in
America and not saying that you can
trust anything in any everything going
on here but at least I think I
understand enough about how things work
I could make a decision about do I trust
this or that but then you've talked
about a certificate from a CA and
country X Y or Z or I don't know
anything about the legal or regulatory
environment in that country or the
business practices I should I even trust
that CA or like how you're giving users
is most users don't even know what a
trust store is you're asking them to
trust certificate authorities from
countries where they may know nothing
about how how much safer is that really
make us when in some cases the
certificate authority is run by the
government itself the government of
Turkey had certificate authority that
was found generating invalid
certificates for google.com those that
certificate authority is no longer
bundled in most operating systems now if
you're really paranoid or if you have
reason to be really paranoid one thing
that might make you feel a little better
is you can always check you can click
the lock icon in your browser and it
will it can't it's incapable of lying
about what certificate authority
actually signed this certificate this
this SSL connection so if you have a
handful that you trust some of the big
players like you know Verisign is pretty
trustworthy
didja cert is pretty trustworthy comodo
is you know maybe maybe mostly
trustworthy then you can check and if
you're really really concerned you know
you can always go in and delete any or
most of these certificate authorities
because the reality is you're not going
to come across certificates signed by a
lot of these I'm looking at my trusted
roots in my Mac and there's one called
Chamber of Commerce root that originates
from the EU somewhere I really don't
think I've ever connected to a website
that was signed by that certificate
authority so let's say that country that
Chamber of Commerce was from I'll just
pick some random EU country say Croatia
that if you lived in Croatia you might
be visiting a lot of Croatian websites
that were using that because it's a
local provider and you might find your
browser didn't work too well if you
deleted it but if you're American you're
not visiting a lot of Croatian websites
that's just one more CA that could
potentially issue certificates for
Google Apple comm and Oracle comm that
you don't really need to have in your
trusted store that's right I think the
average web user doesn't really need to
be that paranoid but definitely when I
see some
that doesn't look right to me I one of
the first things I look at is hey who
signed this certificate you ever see
anything that you didn't expect well one
thing that happens a lot is there's this
concept of what's called TLS middleboxes
so at the risk of oversimplifying the
entire point of SSL TLS is to protect
you against man-in-the-middle attacks
well some corporate users some corporate
administrators say well you know we want
to do antivirus checking before anybody
downloads anything onto our network we
want to make sure that you know nobody's
out you know looking at porn or surfing
YouTube while they're supposed to be
working so we have to be able to inspect
traffic and see what they're doing so
they install a middle box which is a
man-in-the-middle attack and what that
man in the middle attack does is the
company administrator goes through it
installs the root certificate associated
with this middle box on your browser so
that it's implicitly trusted then that
middle box is going to go through every
time you make a request it's gonna
generate falsified certificate on the
fly that your browser will trust and
won't warn you about so you won't see
anything pop up and decrypt your pager
communications check to see if it's
allowed and then re-encrypt it and send
it back on well there have been numerous
instances of these middleboxes
not establishing good security practices
for example one of them left private key
that was associated with their
certificate that was creating these
certificates on the fly unencrypted in a
file that anybody could see which means
that not just this company
administrators could turn around and
generate certificates for any site and
it decrypt anybody's communications but
anybody who happened to know where that
was could do the same thing as a
software engineer chances are you've
crossed paths with MongoDB at some point
whether you're building an app for
millions of users or just figuring out a
side hustle
as the most popular non relational
database MongoDB is intuitive and
incredibly easy for development teams to
use now with MongoDB Atlas you can take
advantage of MongoDB flexible document
data model as a fully automated cloud
service MongoDB Atlas handles all the
costly database operations and admin
tasks you'd rather not spend time on
like security high availability data
recovery monitoring and elastic scaling
try MongoDB Atlas for free today
visit MongoDB comm slash cloud to learn
more we've been talking about corporate
man-in-the-middle boxes a story broke
just recently on security now 724 about
the country of Kazakhstan they are
attempting to require all Internet users
to accept a trusted root certificate
that they have issued so they can
function as a man-in-the-middle for
traffic going in and out of the entire
country
what what's your take on this yeah and
that's not really that surprising it's
been tried before and the the reality is
that with a certificate management
infrastructure that we have there's
really no way to stop them from doing it
but one thing that we all need to be
aware of is that we can't detect when
it's happening we can't stop
man-in-the-middle attacks if somebody
gets ahold of a private key for a
certificate that's installed in our
browser but the browser will never lie
to you about who signed the certificate
of the site that you're visiting so if
you go to facebook.com and it's signed
by digit cert for example you you've got
a pretty good bet that you've got a
legitimate connection whereas if it's
signed by the government of Kazakhstan
and you're in kazakhstan kazakhstan then
you know that you're being spied on
another way that this may be blocked or
run into problems is the browser
manufacturers don't like it there's a
lot of discussion by the browser authors
about considering this certificate to be
a rogue certificate and blocking it in
the browser code do you see that as a
likely vector
for fighting this type of fraudulent
certificate I've seen similar proposals
discussed there have been some Chinese
certificate authorities that have been
found to be untrustworthy in various
instances it'll be interesting to see if
if Firefox for example it goes ahead
with this if chrome follows in their
footsteps or an opera and I mean who
knows even Internet Explorer but even if
they do you know it's that's kind of a
game of whack-a-mole then the Kazakhstan
government can just issue a new one and
require everybody to install that one so
the certificate in transparency
initiative that we talked about earlier
is a good step in the right direction to
protect against that but unfortunately
it's just not as widespread as it needs
to be just yet what you're really
talking about is detecting it when it's
happened right if the rogue actor was
some kind of ISP that was hoping no one
would notice and I got caught and it's
like I okay you got us
we'll stop versus a country where
they're saying yeah we're doing it yeah
what do you do about it right and it's
not clear at all what the penalty for
just refusing to install the certificate
is because it's clear that that could be
detected they'll easily be able to tell
I think they're just a man-in-the-middle
attacking connections to specific Google
endpoints and Facebook and I think
Twitter but they even if somebody is
savvy enough to know to uninstall the
certificate or not install it in the
first place they'll immediately be able
to detect from the traffic that they
didn't have the certificate in place and
they'll know your IP address of the
person who's doing it and it's not clear
if there's any legal penalty for doing
that well the penalties you cannot
access the internet without that
certificate they can block your traffic
that's yeah an ISP could definitely do
that they could just drop the connection
right there
one more counter move that was discussed
was well what if Kazakhstan creates
their own web browser which accepts
their certificate they fork maybe they
fork Firefox
they would have to create a lot of
versions of it for all the platforms
people run is that a feasible counter
move I think they could do it I think
they would find that hard to maintain
over time I think they could very
quickly fork a version of Firefox that
worked on all the brow on all the
popular platforms as they sit today but
they would find that they would need a
very dedicated team of software
developers to keep that running in just
six months from now
I'm also recalling now their attacks
that involve the some type of malware
installing a root certificate on the
machine and then working in
collaboration with men in the middle
server somewhere that now I can issue
certificates for anything that wants
that's right it's it's unfortunate that
it's software installation installing a
certificate is part of standard software
installation one nice thing about using
Linux is they can't do that I want to
move on a little bit now and still
talking about CAS but talk about what is
the process you so Josh you opened a
business Josh's barbecue you want to get
a certificate what are the steps to
getting that certificate it depends on
the certificate authority I've done this
a few times over the years and it's
changed over the years but usually it's
a web form or an email that you fill out
you attach the public key well first you
generate a certificate signing request
that includes a private key file that
you keep private definitely keep it
private and generates what's called a
certificate signing request that has the
subject name that you want in your
certificate and the public key that you
want your certificate along with some
other information that you think is
pertinent and you send that entire
certificate signing request to the
certificate authority then they're going
to get your payment if they take if they
need a payment which most of them do and
they're gonna do some kind of checking
to see if you really are the owner of
the domain you know Josh's barbecue com
now one way they can do that is they can
query the Whois record that that's
associated with that domain name look
for the administrator email and send
that email a challenge which might be
part of your certificate signing request
you know hey this is a certificate
signing request one two three four five
we need you to email us back from this
email address with one two three four
five for example when I did this they
asked me to create a document under my
domain / abc123 dot HTML containing a
certain random-looking number I think
let's encrypt works that way do you
remember the certificate authority I
don't but they're trying to show if I
can add a document under the root path
of that domain I must own the domain or
control it that's right that's another
way that people could do domain control
validation that always makes me just a
little bit nervous because by definition
the site is not yet secure I'm trying to
get the certificate to secure it so
there's this window of vulnerability in
between the time I set up the site and I
get my certificate where somebody else
could potentially man in the middle or
just you know hijack my site and insert
that document and get a certificate for
themselves I I kind of feel like domain
name validation through DNS is a little
a little bit more secure but I will be
honest I've never heard of a hack that
worked quite that way I think they're
relying on that I'm using a browser to
communicate with the CA and that they
give me this random string over an
encrypted channel so nobody else could
know what the random string is to supply
to them and it's at a random path so
you'd have to guess the path or you have
to have hacked on to the web server well
that's if you beat the bad guy to asking
for a certificate for your domain hmm
okay now but we are talking about ways
to attack this this could also be
attacked and this seems to me
be true whether it's email or a web
server through DNS spoofing that's right
huh okay so how would that work
yeah DNS spoofing you know it usually
ends up being a form of cache poisoning
where somebody inserts themselves into
the network and you know remember SSL is
built around the assumption that we're
on a hostile network so you know the
Internet is a packet-switched network
which means that every request you send
and every response you receive is
chopped up into packets and sent over
multiple hops to the ultimate
destination each hop is a computer right
so you know I want to connect to
amazon.com well I don't have a wire from
my computer to amazon.com I have a wire
over I'll have a Wi-Fi connection to
router in my house that's connected to a
wire that's ultimately connected to you
know a router at Verizon then that
router at Verizon looks okay he wants to
get to amazon.com I'm not connected to
amazon.com but I am connected to Cox
Communications that's closer to
amazon.com so all of these routers are
constantly changing exchanging
information telling each other okay I'm
really close to amazon.com I am I'm the
next hop for google.com if you if you've
got Google com send it to me right so a
cache poisoning attack happens when
somebody essentially a malicious actor
lies and says oh hey I'm right next to
amazon.com I'm one hop away from
amazon.com send me all the amazon.com
traffic now they're lying but the
routers don't really have any way to
know about that so the routers suddenly
start trusting this malicious router and
sending traffic to it for amazon.com it
intercepts the traffic modifies it if
it's not using SSL and then sends it on
to over the real route to amazon.com now
the people who are responsible for the
Internet backbone are really good about
staying on top of this but it does still
happen sometimes now you and I as home
users we can't do this if I start
sending
a DNS advertisements over my cable modem
that's gonna set off all kinds of alarm
bells back at my ISP don't ask me how I
know but people with more access to the
Internet backbone can pull off these
kinds of attacks in they'll be caught
but they might be able to do their
damage before they're caught it's very
similar to DNS spoofing would be the BGP
hijacking that's right now I'll link to
there's a paper about that that I'll
link to but and how would that work and
it's essentially the same concept it's
it's setting yourself up to have traffic
routed to you so that you can subvert
the domain validation process before the
actual owner of the domain has a chance
to get at it so in this case I don't
even have to beat you to it I can insert
myself while you're trying to do your
domain validation and trick you into
thinking that you did a domain
validation whereas I did it myself
because I'm intercepting all the packets
that come to you again because we
haven't set up security yet a lot of
these issues center around this point
which you mentioned a couple of times
that once CA is trusted that they there
isn't really anything that prevents them
from issuing a certificate for any one
any bank or e-commerce site that the
trust is maybe too granular that yeah
that that is true and it would be nice
if there was a way to associate certain
certificate authorities to certain
domains as a matter of fact to Google
kicked off an initiative to do exactly
that with public key pinning so the
first time I connect say to Google calm
cool calm is signed by didja certs I
could be wrong so the first time my
browser connects to google.com it says
okay this is this was signed by didja
cert next time I connect I'm gonna make
sure that this certificate is signed by
didja sir
that way if
buddy if somebody has obtained a
fraudulent certificate my browser will
disconnect immediately recognizing that
the certificate was fraudulent it was a
good idea in practice what they found
was that there were a lot of instances
where certificate authorities actually
had reasons to migrate from you know for
example from RSA 1024 bit to 2048 bit so
they had to reissue their own
certificates but public key pinning
would then not trust the new root
certificate so what ended up happening
was us some people that we're using
public key pinning ended up losing
access to their own domains in a way
that they could not easily recover from
so unfortunately public key pinning is
probably not going to be the solution to
that problem I know there's another
initiative which was designed to as a
successor to public key pinning called
certificate transparency you describe
how that worked
yeah the certificate transparency
initiative is interesting it's
essentially a global ledger for every
certificate that's ever issued it uses a
blockchain sort of like Bitcoin for
certificates and when a new certificate
is added to it the old issuer of the
certificate is is hashed into the ledger
so that the certificate authorities
themselves can keep track of hey I I
know I issued a certificate for
google.com I shouldn't see any more
certificates for google.com and it
allows that to be caught really quickly
as a matter of fact Facebook found
multiple instances of FB com
certificates that should not have been
issued I could subscribe or participate
in this blockchain and so said if I'm
Google or Facebook and whenever CA
issues a certificate within whatever
amount of time it takes for the
blockchain to converge you and see it on
this
blockchain and then you at least within
a short time you can detect that
something has gone wrong you didn't
prevent it but you detect it quickly
yeah and hopefully detected it fast
enough before the damage can be done
because it once a once a fraudulent
certificate is obtained it takes a
little while to fish users into it in
the first place so you know it like
everything else with where the public
key infrastructure is involved it's not
perfect but it's what we have the idea
that we need some entity which says
which are the valid issuers of a given
domain that's just that one more layer
of something which assures us that all
the prior layers are correct and then
how do you secure that layer so it's
another example of the turtles all the
way down it is but as long as it starts
off right it stays right okay now
related topic is the revocation of
certificates what are the some of these
cases where you would need to revoke a
certificate right so I start up a
website I get a certificate I get it
signed so now that signature is valid
for a certain period of you know maybe a
year maybe two maybe three years and
because that signature is based on a
mathematical relationship between a
private key and a public key it's it's
gonna be valid forever it's gonna be
valid a thousand years from now so the
if my private key is compromised somehow
then either I have to wait three years
right until the certificate runs out or
I have to have some way of telling the
users that don't use this certificate
anymore this certificate has been
compromised use the new one now the
earliest way that certificate
authorities dealt with that revocation
is that the certificate owner could
contact them it's okay
I got certificate number one two three
four five it's been compromised please
stop using it and the certificate
authority would add that to a
certificate revocation list which
add the number 1 2 3 4 5 to the end of
the list and sign it with its private
key and put that out there somewhere
that browsers could go every once in a
while and check for the list of revoked
certificates well as time got wore on
and more and more domains were generated
and more and more certificates needed to
be revoked those lists got really really
really long so the IETF came up with the
idea of the online certificate status
protocol OCSP where every time the
browser connects to a website gets back
a certificate but then it turns around
and queries the certificate authority
and it says hey I just got certificate 1
2 3 4 5 from this website is this valid
yes or no right so in theory that works
there are a couple problems with it in
practice the first is the certificate
authority has to answer a lot of
requests right you know a big a big
certificate authority like Verisign or
thought you know they've got millions
and millions of certificates and they
could be answering millions and millions
of requests every time somebody connects
to Google they're gonna have to answer
requests so to clarify this request
would occur with every HTTP query that
every single browser is making
potentially that's right yeah and then
another problem is okay what do you do
if this certificate authority doesn't
respond you know they say the
certificates bad you don't use it these
certificates good you do use it but what
if there's they happen to be down do you
just go ahead and connect and that's
what most browsers did they said okay
well I can't talk to Verisign so I'm
just gonna go ahead and trust this as
Adam Langley of the IETF said that's
like a seat belt that snaps when you
crash it works every time except when
you don't need it so and the other
concern that a lot of people had with
OCSP is that every time you connect to
any web site your IP address your
browser is sending a request to that
certificate authority saying hey I
connected to Amazon
now that sets up the certificate
authorities as a clearinghouse for a lot
of user behavior and a lot of people you
know then hey there's people who have
legitimate reasons to be concerned about
privacy and they don't want the
certificate authority to know every
single website that they visited we've
seen in the past that when organizations
have that kind of information they use
it and abuse it so there was a concept
created called OCSP stapling and the
idea behind OCSP stapling says okay it's
still up to the certificate authority to
respond and say yes the certificate is
good or bad but the website itself can
go to the certificate authority get the
OCSP response sign it and include that
in their response as well and that's
typically what people use for revocation
now OCSP stapling
so the OCSP response is included as part
of the handshake now when you're talking
about signing the OCSP response it would
be signed by the CA correct the OCSP
response assigned by the CA but the
stapled response is signed by the
certificates itself okay and that
response is that the certificate has not
been revoked as of the time that the
response was generated I assume those
are good for a certain amount of time
and that the domains themselves need to
refresh it every so often because if it
was too old it's then becoming only
telling you something that was true it's
only the certificate was only not
revoked up until the point where it was
revoked that's right exactly
no CSP response has a validity period of
typically a few days so there is a
window of vulnerability between the time
if you if you are compromised between
the time that you're compromised and the
time that you can really revoke the
certificate but a few days is better
than a few years we're right in close to
the end of time here I wanted to get a
little bit into how how these protocols
work within the browser and a couple of
things we could hit on could you explain
what is the same-origin policy yeah
so when JavaScript became a big thing in
browsers one of the one security
consideration in JavaScript is that
javascript is not allowed to make
external web call out to any domain
except the domain that it was originally
downloaded from so you know I go to
gmail.com and Gmail is gonna turn around
and try and query my Inbox
so that request has to go back to
gmail.com
that's the same-origin policy in
javascript that prevents a java a bad
page from downloading javascript that
turns right around and queries your
Gmail and sends your email responses
back to the the malicious site and I
wanted to use that to lead up to
something called HTTP strict Transport
Security so what problem does that solve
and how does it work
yeah with strict Transport Security HSTs
really is about making sure that
everything on the page if anything is a
SSL then everything is ISO so right so
the way a web request works you know I
go get you know index dot HTML and it
defines a framework for a page but it
has links to things like images and
JavaScript and CSS that are subsequently
fetched by other HTTP requests and it's
been valid since as long as there's been
HTTP for an HTTP page to include
unencrypted HTTP links to images or
JavaScript well what that means is that
if I download the page right the page is
secure but if it downloads you know the
angular framework or the jQuery
framework or any JavaScript a
man-in-the-middle could attack that
JavaScript because it wasn't downloaded
securely and make any modifications he
wants and again in that way take
complete control of my page
so the strict Transport Security this
says okay at the top level if
something's been misconfigured or
attacked in such a way that it looks
like you should be requesting unsecured
don't request it cuz this did not come
from me something related to this we get
these warnings on our browsers about
mixed content well what is the browser
trying to warn us about and that's
exactly what it is it's telling you that
although you connected HTTPS at the top
level you know the images or some of the
images or some of the JavaScript or some
of the CSS we're downloaded using plain
HTTP so there was no protection
associated with them and that that might
or might not be a bad thing you know you
want your JavaScript to it the very
least be protected against modifications
but even images can be a vulnerability
if somebody can go in and swap you know
image buttons so that they look like
they say different things
I understand back in at one point in
time this was more of an economic
decision because SSL was expensive to
terminate as that economics shifted to
where you can encrypt everything now
because the handshake happens once so
we're just talking about encryption as a
cost right be careful
the handshake happens once per HTTP
connection
now H SSL has always allowed session
resumption so that you can reuse already
established SSL keys but there have been
a lot of vulnerabilities associated with
session resumption it's been hard to get
right with the latest version of TLS
that don't seem to be any
vulnerabilities there but there have
been a lot of libraries that turned off
session resumption so in a lot of cases
you do need to do a brand new SSL
handshake for every single request you
request the page you turn around you
request an image that's a new handshake
you request the next image that's a new
handshake
now HTTP 1.1 allows for pipeline request
thank you
HTTP 1.1 allows
for pipelined requests that allow you to
reuse some of that keying material but
even that you know for reasons of
efficiency your browsers probably gonna
open up six or seven connections to the
page or to the website and download so
that's six or seven separate ssl
connections and use that to download the
constituents of the page
however SSL has gotten really fast and
with TLS 1.3 even some of the concerns
around round trips have gotten have been
lessened quite a bit so you know modern
processors can encrypt really fast
most modern processors include AES at
the hardware level so the concerns
around the time that it takes to encrypt
everything are really a non-issue today
and there's there's been a big push for
SSL everywhere for for good reason what
final question which is in this same
vein and this will be my my last
question a common practice to push
non-changing content that doesn't have
any real security value like CSS
stylesheets
maybe images things that don't have a
customer account data in them out to a
content distribution network like
CloudFlare or a commie now how is that
compatible with SSL in that I don't
think I want to give CloudFlare my
private key so they can terminate SSL my
domain but I do want we don't want the
users to get mixed content warning so
how how do we provide security when
we're distributing content out to and
well as long as everything's HTTPS it
doesn't necessarily have to come from
the same domain so I've worked with
Akamai in the past for example you know
we put our images out on you know an
Akamai comm server as long as Akamai
itself has SSL at that Akamai dot-com
domain you don't have any concerns we
mixed content or unencrypted content as
long as they keep up with their SSL so
that was gonna be on my last question
I'm gonna try to fit this one just one
more in what is a what are some of the
developer tools or at least one example
of a tooling for developers for
debugging or working with the TLS well
one that I use all the time is the open
SSL toolkit so if you have open SSL
installed on your computer if you have
OS X or Linux almost definitely have
open SSL installed there's a command
line tool called open SSL that has a lot
of sub commands like you can do key
generation you can do encryption
decryption you can do you can generate
signatures and you can use this really
really useful tool called s underscore
client that actually establishes an SSL
connection but tells you everything is
doing along the way and lets you look
into the bits and bytes of that
connection to debug and see what's going
on great and that wraps up the content
portion in the interview I did mention
your book where can listeners find that
you can also go to the publishers
website at wily dot-com or you can visit
my blog at command-line fanatic calm and
your blog is that the best place for
people who want to find out anything
else you're doing follow you or what
you're thinking about yeah absolutely
I periodically I keep it very completely
technical I don't have anything about
you know my personal opinions or
politics or family on my blog it's a
pure tech blog so just this past month I
published a walkthrough of a TLS 1.3
handshake I decrypted each byte of a
handshake and described what what each
one was for that sounds super useful
well Joshua it's been a great
conversation I really appreciate you
coming on software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me for
software engineering radio this has been
Robert
and thank you for listening thanks for
listening to se Radio an educational
program brought to you by Triple E
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening